Guide to the J. E. Wallace Sterling, President of Stanford University, Papers
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Papers, Series 1
  - Cal Tech: History 5A (Modern History) (Box D1, Folder 17)
    Lectures, notes
  - CBS: Transcripts of Broadcasts by Sterling, 1946-1947 (Box D1, Folder 18)
  - Lectures: Post-War Europe (Box D1, Folder 19)
    includes clipping from 1938, History 105 notes
  - Lectures: Canada at War (Box D1, Folder 20)
    Vista del arroyo
  - Lectures: Problems of International Organization (Box D1, Folder 21)
  - Lectures: Kernal and New Turkey (Box D1, Folder 22)
  - Lectures: France (Box D1, Folder 23)
  - Lectures: Scandinavia - The Middle Way (Box D1, Folder 24)
  - Lectures: The French Hegemony in Europe, 1941 (Box D1, Folder 25)
    Cal Tech
  - Lectures: Germany and the European Situation, 1939 (Box D1, Folder 26)
  - Lectures: Contemporary Italy (Box D1, Folder 27)
    History 107
  - California Centennials Commission, 1949 (Box D1, Folder 28)
    Historical Caravan Kit
  - Manuscript - Untitled, several drafts (Box D1, Folder 29)
    Probably the last chapter for Godfrey Davies "The History of British Foreign Policy Since 1783."
  - The Pacific Specator, 1946-1948 (Box D1, Folder 30)
    Correspondence with Edith Mirrielees
  - Pacific Historical Review, 1939-1947 (Box D1, Folder 31)
  - New America Foundation, 1945-1946 (Box D1, Folder 32)
  - American Association for the United Nations, 1946-1947 (Box D1, Folder 33)
    Sterling was president of Pasadena chapter, resigned 1947
  - Congratulations, Welcomes to Stanford, 1948-1949 (Box D1, Folder 34)
  - Congratulations, Welcomes to Stanford, 1948-1949 (Box D1, Folder 35)
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1948 (Box D1, Folder 36)
  - Class Notes: Constitutional History, British History, Political Theories, 1925 (Box D1, Folder 37)
    Univ. of Toronto
  - Manuscript: Untitled (Box D1, Folder 38)
    Covers Modern British relations, esp. with Russia
  - Manuscript: "1919-1939" (Box D1, Folder 39)
  - Lectures: History 4 "The British Empire" (Box D1, Folder 40)
    Extensive notes for lectures, includes Sterling's drawings of British trade ships through history.
  - Manuscript: "1919 to Locarno" (Box D1, Folder 41)
  - Society of American Historians, 1946-1947 (Box D1, Folder 42)
  - Microphotography, 1939 (Box D1, Folder 43)
    Corresp. with Max Savelle about equipment to make microfilm
  - Correspondence to and from students, 1944-1946 (Box D1, Folder 44)
  - National War College, 1947 (Box D1, Folder 45)
    Sterling's responses to student research topics (all dealing with Soviet expansionism)
  - Notes for current speech (Box D1, Folder 46)
    Includes chronology of proposals for international peace from 1306-1789
  - Manuscript: "1933-1939" (Box D1, Folder 47)
    Reviewers comments on back of file folder
  - Manuscripts: "British Foreign Policy During the War, 1914-1918" and "Peace Conference" (Box D1, Folder 48)
  - Lectures: History 4 "The British Empire" (Box D1, Folder 49)
    Reading list, notes
  - Manuscripts: "At the time of Locarno..." (Box D1, Folder 50)
  - Citizen's Committee for the Municipal Court, 1947 (Box D1, Folder 51)
    Supporters of Prop. 6 for Pasadena Municipal Court
  - New York File, 1945-1946 (Box D1, Folder 52)
    Misc. material (not clearly related to New York)
  - Congratulations on Stanford Presidency, 1949 (Box D1, Folder 53)
    Lots of correspondence
  - Council on Foreign Relations, 1945-1946 (Box D2, Folder 1)
    Corresp.
  - Huntington Library - General, 1948-1949 (Box D2, Folder 2)
  - British Empire - Fiji Data, 1936-1939 (Box D2, Folder 3)
  - Speech - Stanford, 1916-1941 (Box D2, Folder 4)
    Draft manuscript
  - Dissertation Research, 1937-1939 (Box D2, Folder 5)
    Includes resignation as Stanford History Instructor, 1937
  - Manuscript: "Disarmament, 1919-1923..." (Box D2, Folder 6)
    Untitled
  - Congratulations on Stanford Presidency, 1948 (Box D2, Folder 7)
  - Congratulations on Stanford Presidency, 1948 (Box D2, Folder 8)
  - Published Articles, 1935-1945 (Box D2, Folder 9)
    Includes listing of publications
  - Cal Tech Library Newsletter, 1946 (Box D2, Folder 10)
  - Social Science Research Council (SSRC), 1945 (Box D2, Folder 11)
    Pacific Coast Regional Committee
  - Social Science Research Council (SSRC), 1941-1944 (Box D2, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript: Untitled (Box D2, Folder 13)
    Regarding Russia and Britain
  - Personal Correspondence, 1945-1947 (Box D2, Folder 14)
  - Racial Origins and Nativity of Canadian People, 1937 (Box D2, Folder 15)
    Census Report
  - British Empire - Reading Notes (Box D2, Folder 16)
  - Income Tax (Box D2, Folder 17)
  - Clippings announcing Stanford Presidency, 1948 (Box D2, Folder 18)
  - France, 19th Century - Notes (Box D2, Folder 19)
  - Communism and Communist Parties - Notes (Box D2, Folder 20)
    "Russia Going Fascist?"
  - Italy, 19th Century - Notes (Box D2, Folder 21)
  - Humanities Division - Correspondence, 1939-1947 (Box D2, Folder 22)
  - Humanities Division - Books Ordered, 1942 (Box D2, Folder 23)
  - Stanford Conference on American History, 1937-1943 (Box D2, Folder 24)
    Institute of American History at Stanford
  - Western College Association, 1943-1948 (Box D2, Folder 25)
  - Western Personnel Institute - Foreign Service Brochure, 1946 (Box D2, Folder 26)
  - National War College Lecture: "The Pattern of British Foreign Policy", 1947 (Box D2, Folder 27)
  - Western College Association, 1945-1947 (Box D2, Folder 28)
  - Southern California Council of Inter-American Affairs, 1943-1944 (Box D2, Folder 29)
  - Office of Strategic Service, 1942 (Box D2, Folder 30)
    Foreign Nationalities Branch
  - Manuscript: "1919-1939" (Box D2, Folder 31)
  - Photographs: 8 x 10 glossies for CBS (Box D2, Folder 32)
  - Personal Stuff, 1948 (Box D2, Folder 33)
    Includes photos of snow in Pasadena (7), letters from family
  - National War College - General, 1946-1947 (Box D2, Folder 34)
  - Office of Strategic Services, 1942-1943 (Box D2, Folder 35)
  - Letters of Recommendation (for other people), 1944-1946 (Box D2, Folder 36)
  - Social Science Research Council - Fellowship, 1934-1939 (Box D2, Folder 37)
    Sterling worked in Canda on this fellowship
  - Humanities Division - Correspondence, 1943-1947 (Box D2, Folder 38)
  - Munro, W.B., 1937-1944 (Box D2, Folder 39)
    Correspondence regarding Sterling's appointment at Cal Tech
  - Publishers - Corresp. to and from, 1942-1947 (Box D2, Folder 40)
  - Humanities Division: History 15 materials, 1946 (Box D2, Folder 41)
  - Sophomore History - Books for Library, 1939-1940 (Box D2, Folder 42)
  - Contributions, 1944-1946 (Box D2, Folder 43)
  - Bills Paid, 1944-1946 (Box D2, Folder 44)
    Books, subscriptions
  - East and West Association, 1944-1945 (Box D2, Folder 45)
  - Cal Tech Alumni Association, 1939-1947 (Box D2, Folder 46)
  - Class Notes - Political Science 114 "Foreign Service", 1932 (Box D3, Folder 1)
  - Class Notes - Political Science 121 "League of Nations" (Box D3, Folder 2)
  - Notes: England (Box D3, Folder 3)
  - Exams: History 11, 12 "Western Civilization", 1937 (Box D3, Folder 4)
  - Exams and Syllabi: History 9, 10, 1937 (Box D3, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript: "German Efforts to Secure British Neutrality, 1914" (Box D3, Folder 6)
  - Outlines: History 9 "Russia in the 19th Century" and History 8 "Napoleon" (Box D3, Folder 7)
  - Lecture - "Winning the Peace" (Box D3, Folder 8)
  - Lecture - "Munich Agreement - Peace or Postponement" (Box D3, Folder 9)
  - Naval War College, 1947 (Box D3, Folder 10)
    "National Policy and Its Influence on Naval Strategy" lecture was given at the college, 8/16/47
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Catalog Dept., 1948 (Box D3, Folder 11)
    Budget request
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Friends of the Huntington, 1948 (Box D3, Folder 12)
    Articles of Incorporation and By-Laws of the group.
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Friends' Day, 1948 (Box D3, Folder 13)
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Library Division, 1948 (Box D3, Folder 14)
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Price, Waterhouse & Co., 1947 (Box D3, Folder 15)
    Report and financial statements - 6/30/47
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Publications, 1948 (Box D3, Folder 16)
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Publications Committee, 1948 (Box D3, Folder 17)
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Reference Dept., 1948 (Box D3, Folder 18)
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Research Group, 1948 (Box D3, Folder 19)
  - Henry E. Huntington Library - Financial Reports, 1948 (Box D3, Folder 20)
  - Letters of Rcommendation, 1947 (Box D3, Folder 21)
  - C.B.S. - Correspondence with Sponsors, 1943-1945 (Box D3, Folder 22)
  - C.B.S.- 10:15 p. m. Broadcast, 1945-1946 (Box D3, Folder 23)
  - C.B.S. - General, 1943-1947 (Box D3, Folder 24)
    "Scrap Book" materials, including photos and pamphlets.
  - C.B.S. - Correspondences, 1942-1947 (Box D3, Folder 25)
  - C.B.S. - Contracts, 1942-1945 (Box D3, Folder 26)
  - C.B.S. - Citizens Trust and Savings Bank, 1947 (Box D3, Folder 27)
  - Radio - General, 1943-1944 (Box D3, Folder 28)
    Distinct from C.B.S
  - Notes - Western Civilization, Autumn, 1936 (Box D3, Folder 29)
  - Notes - "Historiography" (Box D3, Folder 30)
  - Notes - Europe 19th Century (Box D3, Folder 31)
    History 105, "General Works on the History of Europe, 1815-1871"
  - Notes - Post-War Europe (Box D3, Folder 32)
  - Lectures - 19th Century Europe (Box D3, Folder 33)
  - Notes and Papers - Europe 19th Century (Box D3, Folder 34)
    Papers include "The Development of Liberalism in Europe 1848-1871" and "Why the Zollverein Helped to Unify Germany whereas the Austrian Tariff Union Did Not" both for a Prof. Higby.
  - Notes- "Historiography" - Winter Quarter, 1931 (Box D3, Folder 35)
  - Lecture Notes - History 12 "Europe Since 1789", 1945 (Box D3, Folder 36)
  - Notes - German Class (Box D3, Folder 37)
  - Notes - History 103 and History 164 - 19th Century Europe (Box D3, Folder 38)
  - Lectures - "Canada and the Empire" (Box D3, Folder 39)
  - Lectures - "Balance Sheet of the War" (Box D3, Folder 40)
  - Lectures - "Can the British Empire Survive?" (Box D3, Folder 41)
  - Lectures - "What Makes a Revolution?" (Box D3, Folder 42)
  - Lectures - "World War B" (Box D3, Folder 43)
  - Lectures - "The War" (Box D3, Folder 44)
  - Lectures - "War Strategy & War Politics" (Box D3, Folder 45)
  - Lectures - "The Stop Hitler Movement" (Box D3, Folder 46)
  - Lectures - "Soviet Foreign Policy", 1937 (Box D3, Folder 47)
  - Lectures - "The Changing Aspect of the War", 1942 (Box D3, Folder 48)
  - Lectures - "Nazi Controlled Europe", 1941 (Box D3, Folder 49)
  - Lectures - "The War Resources of the Allied Nations - Europe and Russia" (Box D3, Folder 50)
  - Lectures - "Reconstruction Planning in Canada" (Box D3, Folder 51)
  - Lectures - "The Battle of Russia", 1941 (Box D3, Folder 52)
  - Lectures - "The War in Review and in Prospect", 1942 (Box D3, Folder 53)
  - Lectures - "The Second Front and a Global War" (Box D3, Folder 54)
  - Lectures - "The United States and World War II" (Box D3, Folder 55)
  - Center for International Understanding, 1946 (Box D3, Folder 56)
  - Humanities Division: History 8 "History of Russia", 1944-1946 (Box D3, Folder 57)
  - Western Civilization, Winter Quarter, 1937 (Box D3, Folder 58)
    Stanford
  - Manuscript: "French Revolution" (Box D3, Folder 59)
  - European History, 1600-1932 (Box D3, Folder 60)
    Lectures, syllabi
  - History 7, 8, 9: Europe 1500 - (Box D3, Folder 61)
  - History 12: Charles Darwin lecture by Sterling, 1937 (Box D3, Folder 62)
    Includes notes for other lectures by other people
- Hoover Institution files, Series 2
  - Library--Hoover, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Library--Hoover, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Hoover Institute and Library, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Hoover Institute and Library, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Hoover Institute and Library, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Hoover Institute and Library, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hoover Library, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Hoover Institute and Library, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hoover Institute and Library, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hoover Institution, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hoover Institution, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Hoover Institution, air conditioning and buglar alarm system, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Hoover Library, 1961 Oct (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hoover Institution, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Hoover Institution, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Hoover Institute, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Old file from Sterling's desk sent to Central Files 1961 Sep 1.
  - Hoover Library Advisory Board Annual Reports, 1956-1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Hoover Advisory Board, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Hoover Advisory Board (invitations-expansion), 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Invitations and acceptances only.
  - Hoover Institution, ICA proposal, Provosts' copy (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Hoover Institution, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Hoover Institution, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hoover Institution, 1962-1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Hoover Library Advisory Board, 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
  - Hoover Library Advisory Board and University Committee, 1953-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Hoover Institution and Library -- Fund Raising, 1955 Sep 1 - 1957 Sep 13 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Hoover Campaign Meetings, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Hoover Institution Campaign - General, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Hoover Institution Budget, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Herbert Hoover, Personal, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Herbert Hoover, Personal, 1952-1964 (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
  - Hoover Institution, 1960-1963 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Hoover Library on War, Revolution, and Peace (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Hoover Institution, Uncommon Man Award and Dedication of the Herbert Hoover Room, 1965 Jul 20 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Trustees Committee on Hoover Institution, 1960-1962 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Trustees Committee on Hoover Institution, 1960-1962 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Hoover Advisory Board, 1962-1966 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
  - Hoover Institution, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Hoover Institution, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Hoover Institution, 1964-1966 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Hoover Advisory Board, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Hoover Institution, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Hoover Institution, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Hoover Advisory Board, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 9)